<?xml version="1.0"?>
<configuration>
	<placeholders>
		<placeholder id="template_name">Salesforce and Database User Bidirectional Sync</placeholder>
	</placeholders>
	<sections>
		<section id="use_case">
I want to have my users synchronized between Salesforce and Database organizations

## Template overview <a name="templateoverview"/>

Let's say we want to keep Salesforce synchronized with Database. Then, the integration behavior can be summarized just with the following steps:

1. Ask Salesforce:
> *Which changes have there been since the last time I got in touch with you?*

2. For each of the updates fetched in the previous step (1.), ask Database:
> *Does the update received from A should be applied?*

3. If Database answer for the previous question (2.) is *Yes*, then *upsert* (create or update depending each particular case) Database with the belonging change

4. Repeat previous steps (1. to 3.) the other way around (using Database as source and Salesforce as the target)

 Repeat *ad infinitum*:

5. Ask Salesforce:
> *Which changes have there been since the question I've made in the step 1.?*

And so on...
  
The question for recent changes since a certain moment is nothing but a [poller](https://developer.mulesoft.com/docs/display/current/Poll+Reference) with a watermark defined.
		</section>
		<section id="considerations">
<![CDATA[
**Note:** This particular Anypoint Template illustrate the synchronization use case between SalesForce and a Database, thus it requires a DB instance to work.
The Anypoint Template comes packaged with a SQL script to create the DB table that it uses. 
It is the user responsibility to use that script to create the table in an available schema and change the configuration accordingly.
The SQL script file can be found in [src/main/resources/sfdc2jdbc.sql](../master/src/main/resources/sfdc2jdbc.sql)

This template is customized for MySQL. To use it with different SQL implementation, some changes are necessary:

* update SQL script dialect to desired one
* replace MySQL driver library dependency to desired one in [POM](pom.xml)
* replace attribute `driverClassName` of `db:generic-config` element with class name of desired JDBC driver in [src/main/app/config.xml](../master/src/main/app/config.xml)
* update JDBC URL in `mule.*.properties` file

There are a couple of things you should take into account before running this template:

1. **Users cannot be deleted in SalesForce:** For now, the only thing to do regarding users removal is disabling/deactivating them, but this won't make the username available for a new user.
2. **Each user needs to be associated to a Profile:** SalesForce's profiles are what define the permissions the user will have for manipulating data and other users. Each SalesForce account has its own profiles. Check out the next section to define a map between Profile Ids (from the source account to the ones in the target account and the other way around).
]]>
		</section>
		<section id="application_configuration">
		<![CDATA[
+ poll.frequencyMillis `10000`  
This are the milliseconds (also different time units can be used) that will run between two different checks for updates in Salesforce and Database
+ page.size `200`


### SalesForce Connector configuration
+ sfdc.username `jorge.drexler@mail.com`
+ sfdc.password `Noctiluca123`
+ sfdc.securityToken `avsfwCUl7apQs56Xq2AKi3X`
+ sfdc.url `https://login.salesforce.com/services/Soap/u/32.0`
+ sfdc.integration.user.id `005n0000000T3QkAAK`
+ sfdc.watermark.default.expression `2015-08-25T11:00:00.000Z`  
This property is an important one, as it configures what should be the start point of the synchronization. The date format accepted in SFDC Query Language is either *YYYY-MM-DDThh:mm:ss+hh:mm* or you can use Constants. [More information about Dates in SFDC](https://help.salesforce.com/HTViewSolution?id=000004680&language=en_US)

### Database Connector configuration for
+ db.jdbcUrl `jdbc:mysql://localhost:3306/mule?user=mule&password=mule`
+ db.integration.user.id `mule@localhost`
+ db.watermark.default.expression `2015-08-25 11:00:00.000` 
This property is an important one, as it configures what should be the start point of the synchronization. 


+ from.sfdc.to.db.profilesMap `['00r80000001CEiGAAW': '00e80000110CDfGMAX','00e30000000ifQyAAI': '00q70000000fiQyEZI']`  
+ from.db.to.sfdc.profilesMap `['00r80000001CEiGAAW': '00e80000110CDfGMAX','00e30000000ifQyAAI': '00q70000000fiQyEZI']`  
The meaning of the properties above is defined in the second consideration on [the previous section](#afewconsiderations)
]]>
		</section>
		<section id="api_calls">
		<![CDATA[
Salesforce imposes limits on the number of API Calls that can be made. Therefore calculating this amount may be an important factor to consider. The Anypoint Template calls to the API can be calculated using the formula:

***1 + X + X / 200***

Being ***X*** the number of Users to be synchronized on each run. 

The division by ***200*** is because, by default, Users are gathered in groups of 200 for each Upsert API Call in the commit step. Also consider that this calls are executed repeatedly every polling cycle.	

For instance if 10 records are fetched from origin instance, then 12 api calls will be made (1 + 10 + 1).
]]>
		</section>
		<section id="default_endpoints_xml">
		<![CDATA[
This file should contain every inbound and outbound endpoint of your integration app. It is intended to contain the application API.
In this particular template, this file contains a couple of poll inbound endpoints that query Salesforce and database for updates using watermark as mentioned before.
]]>
		</section>
		<section id="default_business_logic_xml">
		<![CDATA[
This file holds the functional aspect of the template (points 2. to 4. described in the [template overview](#templateoverview)). Its main component is a [*Batch job*][8], and it includes *steps* for both executing the synchronization from Salesforce to Database, and the other way around.
]]>
		</section>
	</sections>
</configuration>